Yuri Dolzhneko

Full stack software engineer

+31 (0) 634883558 | yuridolzhenko.com | yuri.dolzhenko@gmail.com

Summary

Full stack java developer with about 10 years of experience in designing, developing and maintaining software solutions for large international finance and insurance companies.

Keywords

Expertise: Internet/Intranet software solutions design and development, RESTful API's, microservices, requirements definition, data analysis, database design

Process: agile, scrum, devops, prototyping, continuous integration and delivery

Tools: Java, Groovy, Spring Framework, Maven, JPA, Hibernate, Junit, Mockito, SQL, Oracle, MySQL, MongoDB, R, JavaScript, TypeScript, NodeJS, Bower, JQuery, Ext JS, D3.js, AngularJS 1/2, XML, JSON, Unix, Bash, Docker, Tomcat, Git, SonarQube, Jira, Confluence, Bamboo, Jenkins

Experience

- 2014 - present, Qualogy, (http://www.qualogy.nl), The Netherlands

Consultant

After three years of working on the same type datasources of products, I felt like I have to do something else, so I started to work for Qualogy as a consultant in 2014 and from the first day joined one of the ING bank's teams to help them with their brand new omnichannel initiative (basically same API endpoints serving data for all channels, from self-service portals for private and business customers to call centers and bank' branches). RESTful APIs that we are building (Spring and Jersey backed) for us are bridges between Angular JS frontends and TIBCO infrastructure (to which we connected through Netflix' Hystrix), which actually has access to all of the bank' datasources. I'm part of one of many *agile* (Yaaay! Agile and scrum are now everywhere, so you can even become a *certified* scrum team.) feature-teams consisted of product owner, frontend, backend and tibco developers (typically around 5-9 people), so we can develop our pieces of functionality independently (well, relatively). Besides developing APIs themselves, I'm also working on actual frontends that consume data from thoose. While mainly I'm busy with developing and delivering of the old and new functionality, I also started to make a presentations about our APIs ecosystem and guide newcomers, so they can get on track quickly.

- 2011 - 2014, Secondfloor (<u>www.secondfloor.com</u>), The Netherlands

Java developer

I had never thought about moving to the Netherlands, but today you never know where you will end up tomorrow. One of many Dutch recruitment companies reached me at LinkedIn and asked if I was interested in having an interview with one of theirs clients. «Why not?» - I replied. After a couple of talks I found myself packing stuff and moving to Amsterdam. Company that I started working for, was all about risk management, reporting and compliance tools for insurance and finance companies. There I was working on a product, jointly created by us and IBM (requirements were coming from IBM, we were working on the implementation, while IBM was selling the final product to their customers). It was a tool that was used for collection of structured and unstructured data, for reporting and decision making. Application was Spring-backed (MVC, security, JMS) and connected to Oracle or DB2 databases (using Hibernate for the most things and JDBC for some of them). It exposed a RESTful APIs for third-parties and for our own frontend that was built using Ext JS. We had a team of one project manager who did all the planning, three to seven developers to actually develop what was planned, couple of testers to test things and business analyst who was busy with writing specifications together with analysts from IBM. I was working on

both backend and frontend parts of the application and busy with delivering binaries, fixing issues that came from testers in our test environments and supporting clients and real production systems.

- 2009-2011, Luxoft (http://www.luxoft.ru/), Russia

Senior java developer, lead java developer

Luxoft is one the biggest IT consultancy companies in eastern Europe, with the huge portfolio of clients, including Boeing, Deutsche Bank and UBS. I failed first interview there when I first came to Moscow and I succeeded one year later. I joined one of the many dev teams that company had on-site at UBS bank. We worked on application that was effectively a frontend to multiple bank's datasources that contained information about financial instruments. It was used for CRUD operations on the latter (including cross-datasource operations, i.e. querying an object in one datasource and saving it in another). We had to replace old swing-based desktop solution that had performance issues with the new, intranet-based one (spring mvc, with freemarker templates and Jquery / Jquery UI on the frontend). Being a truly software company in Luxoft we made use of most techniques and tools that were available and popular to use to support our work, Jira for issues tracking, Confluence for knowledge keeping and Bamboo for CI, and that was the time, when agile and scrum just started to get its hype, so our daily catch up instantly became scrum meetings, during which we could only stand! We had four developers (all in Moscow), testing team in Bangalore and product owner in Boston. We maintained and supported four instances of the application in four different time zones and that guaranteed us lots of fun when it came to communication: catch up calls/meetings in the evenings because of Boston's time zone, and bunches of issues every morning because of Bangalore's time zone. While working on the project, my responsibilities grew from just developing of a new functionality and bug fixing to deploying releases to production, supporting customers and planning changes upfront.

- 2008-2009, Intouch Insurance (http://www.in-touch.ru), Russia

Java developer

I moved to Moscow to pursue career advancement opportunities - there weren't many things to work on in my hometown. I immediately joined in-house development team of "Intouch insurance", a pioneer company in direct insurance (i.e. with sales only through internet or call centers, with no third parties involved) in Russia. Team was responsible for maintaining and extending company's CRM system, performance of which, due to company's sales model, was mission-critical. CRM was based on <u>IDIT Insurance framework</u>, which, in turn, was built on top of Struts web framework. Application covered all the business processes that are typical to insurance company - policy sales, claims handling and payments management and we had a lot of new functionality to create while theting it to Russian insurance policies and laws (and weird reality). We had a pretty much typical web application configuration for that time - JSP's, Struts servlets, Java EE's JDO to connect to Oracle database and a pinch of javascript on a frontend side. There I had my first experience of working in a distributed team - core framework team was located in Warsaw, Poland and we managed to work together efficiently and flexibly (no word "agile" was on horizon yet, though we used Jira) - teams sometimes traveled to each other, though daily things issues were communicated through emails and Skype good enough.

2007-2008, Rostelecom (http://www.rostelecom.ru/), Russia

Java developer

I started my career as a java developer in the biggest Russian landline telecommunications company. I was working in a chapter of the IT department, where we worked on various small-to-medium sized intranet applications used by company's employees for very different reasons - starting from internal HR tools and finishing with customer's profiles management applications (typically, struts-powered servlets, running on Tomcat that were connected to Oracle databases using mainly JDBC). There I had my first experience with what later will be called single page applications and RESTful API's - first version of Google's GWT framework was released around that time and we adopted it for couple of our projects. No one heard of Jira, agile, test driven development or devops back then, but we were responsible for everything starting from initial design to production deployment and support.

Personal projects and research

I'm not limiting myself to only working in office 40 hours a week. In our craft we are having hard time keeping pace with things and technologies that are moving forward and changing sometimes way too fast. To stay aligned and share knowledge, I'm writing <u>blog posts</u> (not that often, but I'm working on it) and doing homebrew <u>projects</u> and researches (mostly around data analysis and visualization, since I'm a mathematician and love it when things are

looking good visually). That keeps me in shape and allows to touch and try new things (that is not always possible in conservative and slow enterprise environments).

Education & certification

- 2001-2006, Mathematician, system programmer (master degree)

Kuban State University, Krasnodar, Russia

- 2013, Certified Spring Professional

VMWare training & certification

- 2012, MongoDB Developer

10Gen training & certification